David Hamburg MD Papers Finding Aid
Oskar Diethelm Library
- Scholars and World Leaders
  - Hillary R. Clinton, 2001 - 2010; Hamburg has had a long friendship with Hillary R. Clinton since he worked with her on an advisory committee on education before her husband became President. During Bill Clinton’s Presidency they worked together on education issues and he encouraged her to pursue more international activities. The extensive correspondence as part of this archive is compiled in one document, 1/02/2001 – 9/10/2010, which is sequenced with the most recent correspondence first, and hard copies are also available. Highlights include letters of 8/28, 11/16, and 12/09/2009 in which Hamburg advises Clinton regarding the USAID. Hamburg’s letter of 8/28 includes an adaptation of his book chapter on development and the prevention of mass violence (saved separately in the overall Clinton folder) and his letter of 11/16 recommends Sadako Ogata as an excellent contact person for improving the USAID. Clinton’s letter to Hamburg of 12/09 thanks him for his assistance and indicates her plans to contact Mrs. Ogata. Hamburg’s letter to Clinton of 11/18/2008 encourages her to take the position of Secretary of State and describes their interactions together while she was First Lady. On 1/24/2002, Clinton sent Hamburg a handwritten letter expressing her regrets for missing Cyrus Vance’s funeral and remarking that, “he was lucky to have such a friend and colleague as you.” (Box 3)
  - Jimmy Carter and Rosalynn Carter, 2002 - 2009; Hamburg and his wife Beatrix worked with Jimmy and Rosalynn Carter as advisors during Carter’s Presidency. During the Carter Administration, David Hamburg worked with Carter in his capacity as president of the Institute of Medicine, as an advisor on key public health issues. Later, the Carnegie Corporation of New York under Hamburg’s presidency provided funding to the Carter Center. Carter served on the Carnegie Commission on Science, Technology, and Government, which led to a task force on development cooperation co-chaired by Carter and Boutros-Boutros Ghali. Hamburg served on the Carter Center’s Advisory Board through 2009. Their correspondence indicates a relationship of mutual respect and support. The extensive correspondence as part of this archive is compiled in one document, 3/20/2002 to 11/05/2009, which is sequenced with the most recent correspondence first, and hard copies are also available. Of particular interest is Carter’s most recent letter to Hamburg on 11/05/2009, in reference to Hamburg’s impending resignation from the Carter Center Board, in which Carter writes, “I look forward to seeing you again at our November meeting. As always, it will be an occasion for recollections of the way our lives have been intertwined over the past 30 years. There is little doubt that The Carter Center and I have been the greatest beneficiaries.” Their correspondence of October 2002 pertains to Carter’s receipt of the Nobel Peace Prize, and Carter writes to Hamburg, “your constant inspiration and motivation, your guidance, counsel, and service are crucial to our progress and the many people we help around the world. We all share the honor of the Nobel Peace Prize.” (Box 3)
  - Graham Allison, 2004; Hamburg’s work with Graham Allison, scholar and leader in political science and government, began during Hamburg’s presidency of Carnegie and has covered many domains, including nuclear non-proliferation and preventing deadly conflict. Hamburg also served on the Advisory Board of the Belfer Center for Science and International Affairs, for which Graham Allison was the director. (Box 3)
  - Frederik Willem de Klerk, 2005 - 2006; During his presidency of Carnegie, Hamburg worked with Frederik Willem de Klerk and Desmond Tutu in efforts to end apartheid and later served as adviser to de Klerk in his founding of the Global Leadership Foundation (this more recent correspondence is part of the archive). (Box 3)
  - John Packer and Max Van der Stoel, 2005 - 2011; International Scholar and Diplomacy expert John Packer was a key advisor to Hamburg in establishing both the UN and EU initiatives. In 2006, Packer invited Hamburg to be part of a discussion on “Operational Conflict Prevention” initiated by OSCE High Commissioner Max Van der Stoel and Jan Eliasson (see letter dated 8/16/2006) and part of Van der Stoel’s work to “Enhance Diplomatic Means of Preventing Violent Conflict” (see 2005 Overview of Van der Stoel Initiative). Hamburg and Packer corresponded on 4/29/2011 regarding the passing of Van der Stoel. (Box 3)
  - Barack Obama, 2008 - 2009; Hamburg’s contacts with Barack Obama were facilitated in many ways by Newton Minow, who was a mentor to Obama in the early part of his career and remained in contact as an informal advisor following his inauguration. Highlights include a letter to Obama on 5/20/2009, in which Hamburg commends Obama for his remarks at the “Holocaust Days of Remembrance Ceremony” and encourages him to take further steps on the question raised in his speech, “How do we ensure that ‘never again’ isn’t an empty slogan, or merely an aspiration, but also a call to action?” Hamburg was invited by Obama to a meeting “on lessons learned from the swine flu experience in 1976-77” due to Hamburg’s efforts work with the Carter Administration during that time period. His letter to Obama on 7/06/2009 reflects on the meeting and expresses hope that “my work on prevention of genocide will be helpful to you and the Secretary of State.” Hamburg’s message to Minow of 7/07/2009 provides further information about the meeting with Obama and offer to ‘take Minow up on his offer’ to prepare a draft speech for Obama on the prevention of genocide. That draft is dated 11/11/2009 and was submitted by Minow to Obama’s chief speechwriter. In August 2011, Hamburg attended meetings at the White House in connection with Obama’s determination to establish an Atrocities Prevention Board (see August 3, 2011 New York Times article, “Obama Takes Steps to Help Avert Atrocities”). (Box 3)
  - Office of War Crimes Issues, 2009; In 2009, Hamburg made contact with the State Department’s Office of War Crimes Issues. Members of the office reached out to Hamburg in connection with the Second Human Right’s Forum in Budapest and expressed interest in orienting their work towards prevention of genocide. (Box 3)
- Written work
  - Documentary on Preventing Genocide, 2007 - 2010 (Box 4)
  - Press/Interviews, 2008 (Box 4)
  - Overview Material/Publications on Preventing Genocide, 2008 - 2010 (Box 4)
  - Autobiographical Statements Re: Work in Preventing Mass Violence, 2009 - 2010 (Box 4)
  - Lectures and Key Documents related to Prevention, 2004 - 2010 (Box 4)